A Guide to the Additional Papers of Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1874-1953
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 March 15-30, 16 items. (Box-folder 19:2)
    Ada wrote that her favorite aunt, Helen died of an angina pectoris. She also wrote that Tom's sister Lavinia was going to Buena Vista to see Tom's mother and would cause Tom's mother too much work with all of her sewing. Ada wrote that the streets in Winchester were still flooded. Tom enclosed a program from the Virginia School of the Deaf and Blind recital.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 April, 24 items. (Box-folder 19:3)
    Ada wrote that they must wait to marry until August because she did not have any money and it was not wise to marry until he had more headway financially. She also instructed him to not take anything from his mother, as Ada did not want to be dependent on anyone. Tom wrote about playing Down in Dixie for the West Augusta Guards at the opera house. He also wrote that she should find a "coloured girl about 14 or near" that she could train to be her servant and maid.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 May, 13 items. (Box-folder 19:4)
    Ada mentioned spending time with her friend George Shoenfelt, painting her room, and looking forward to living with Tom in Staunton.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 June, 12 items. (Box-folder 19:5)
    Ada wrote about their wedding plans and cautioned Tom not to work too hard.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 July, 5 items. (Box-folder 19:6)
    Tom went to Capon Springs to teach music for the summer. Tom wrote about his neighbor Mrs. Jaffe who was helping him to find a cook and set up housekeeping.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 August, 10 items. (Box-folder 19:7)
    Ada wrote about her wedding dress of crepe de chine, wedding rings and a trunk from her father. Tom wrote about wedding invitations to give to Mr. Bantz.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 September, 8 items. (Box-folder 19:8)
    Ada was worried about leaving her mother alone and wanted Tom to let her visit her mother often. Ada would stay with her mother for long periods of time and Tom was lonesome.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1902 December, 1 item. (Box-folder 19:9)
    Tom wrote to Ada when she was visiting her parents in Winchester.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1903 January-July, 13 items. (Box-folder 19:10)
    Ada visited her mother often because Mrs. Bantz was not well. Ada wrote to Tom that it was a "sin" that he had to work so much. She also mentioned their housekeeper, Mary Jackson.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1903 August, 15 items. (Box-folder 19:11)
    Ada and Tom wrote about housekeeping while Ada was in Winchester.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1903 September 1-12, 19 items. (Box-folder 20:1)
    Tom wrote her that he was so glad that she had been happy in their first year of marriage and he appreciated her telling him so. Ada wrote that her mother was having heart problems.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1903 September 16-29, 13 items. (Box-folder 20:2)
    Tom was lonesome and wondered if something were to happen to him, would anyone find him. He also enclosed a music program for his twenty-fourth Organ Recital at the Trinity Church in Staunton. Ada wrote that she was sorry she could not be home with him.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1903 October, 8 items. (Box-folder 20:3)
    Tom wrote that he was teaching at the Virginia Female Institute [Stuart Hall] and if his work remained steady at the Mary Baldwin Seminary he might have to give up working at the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1904 January-September, 20 items. (Box-folder 20:4)
    Ada wrote that if Tom was not feeling better, she would be coming home.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1904 July-December, 11 items. (Box-folder 20:5)
    Tom missed Ada so much when she went to Winchester.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1905 March-August, 15 items. (Box-folder 20:6)
    Ada wrote about Holmes Byrd who died from substance abuse and she thought if he had left alcohol and drugs alone he would have been one of the smartest lawyers in Virginia. Tom wrote to Ada about missing her, desiring her physically, and about wanting a child.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1905 September-December, 19 items. (Box-folder 20:7)
    Ada wrote about a monument for her mother.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1906, 8 items. (Box-folder 20:8)
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1907-1908, 20 items. (Box-folder 20:9)
    Ada wrote to Tom from Winchester that another Sunday at her father's house would send her to Western State. She felt that she was not needed and wanted to go home to Staunton. Tom was working for the Y.M.C.A.; was the Musical Director of the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind; Director of the Stonewall Brigade Band; and Director of the Staunton Philharmonic Orchestra. Tom wrote about buying a new Ford for seven hundred dollars. On their fifth wedding anniversary Tom wrote about his physical desire for her. There is also mention of a friend who was under the care of Dr. DeJarnette, who directed Western State and was the leading proponent of eugenics.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1909, 18 items. (Box-folder 20:10)
    Ada wrote about her dancing classes and about how Tom's niece Tillie Topping could almost walk. They also wrote about their trips to Atlantic City for vacation.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1910 June-November, 27 items. (Box-folder 20:11)
    Tom wrote about hearing the Marine Band play its first concert at the White House. Ada wrote about reports of Negro troops and the question of whether they were in camps or not. Tom was teaching in Capon Springs for the summer. Ada stayed with her father in Winchester during the day. She also wrote that [Allen Caperton] Braxton was telling the people of Winchester how to run a city.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1911 February- August, 15 items. (Box-folder 20:12)
    Ada's father died in February 1911. Ada visited the Hall and the Rouss family in New York.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1912-1914, 16 items. (Box-folder 21:1)
    Tom went on vacation in Atlantic City and New York sunbathing, attending shows, and clubs.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1915 July-August; December, 20 items. (Box-folder 21:2)
    Tom was away at summer camp with the Y.M.C.A. from July through August. In December he wrote to Ada while he was in New York on music business.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1915 July-August; December, 11 items. (Box-folder 21:3)
    Tom attended the Danguard Player Action School in New York and taught summer camp at Terra Alta in West Virginia. He received a wire that his mother had passed away.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1917-1920, 9 items. (Box-folder 21:4)
    Tom taught in Camp Terra Alta in West Virginia during the summers; Ada traveled out west to Los Angeles, California, and Colorado.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1922 July-August, 7 items. (Box-folder 21:5)
    Tom taught in Camp Terra Alta in West Virginia for the summer.
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, 1924 July-August; 1926, 13 items. (Box-folder 21:6)
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth correspondence, n. d., 25 items. (Box-folder 21:7)
  - Tom and Ada Beardsworth general correspondence WWI, Camp Lee, 1918-1919, 27 items. (Box-folder 21:8)
  - Other correspondence, [1859]-1860, 45 items. (Box-folder 21:9)
  - Mary Baker, 1897-1918, 12 items. (Box-folder 22:1)
  - Sophye Baker, 1918; 1942, 2 items. (Box-folder 22:2)
    [Aunt] of William Baker Powell.
  - Shirley Carter to Ada (Hansborough & Carter), 1899-1920, 39 items. (Box-folder 22:3)
    There is correspondence from Ada's attorney about real estate.
  - Shirley Carter to Ada (Hansborough & Carter), 1921-1939, 28 items. (Box-folder 22:4)
  - Colonel Harry LaT Cavenaugh (WWI hero with monument in San Francisco) to Ada, 1933-1951, 7 items. (Box-folder 22:5)
  - Will R. Chapin University of Virginia, 1896-1897, 6 items. (Box-folder 22:6)
    Roommate of William Glass.
  - J. Peyton Clark, 1899, 1 item. (Box-folder 22:7)
  - Martha B. Clark "Mat," 1900-1907, 17 items. (Box-folder 22:8)
  - Mary Johnson Clark (Mrs. Theodor Megaarden), 1892-1923; n. d., 16 items. (Box-folder 22:9)
  - Mary Judge William Clark, 1894, 4 items. (Box-folder 22:10)
  - Barnett McFee Clinedinst, 1896, 5 items. (Box-folder 22:11)
  - Floridus and John Crosby, 1913-1937, 9 items. (Box-folder 22:12)
  - Frank R. Gillis, 1894 March-December, 25 items. (Box-folder 22:13)
    Frank Gillis was a successful and well known playwright who wanted to leave his wife for Ada. She was only interested in his friendship and his contacts.
  - Frank R. Gillis, 1895 January-June, 27 items. (Box-folder 22:14)
  - Frank R. Gillis, 1895 August-1896 December, 15 items. (Box-folder 22:15)
  - Frank R. Gillis, 1897 January-May, 19 items. (Box-folder 22:16)
  - J. Gilpatric and other Pen Pals, 1894-1895, 19 items. (Box-folder 23:1)
  - William Wood Glass and Ada Bantz, 1892-1894, 22 items. (Box-folder 23:2)
    William Glass dated Ada in high school and wrote to her while he attended the University of Virginia. His letters were about life at the University including drinking, gambling, the Glee Club, a small pox scare, and vaccinations. He also included programs for the University of Virginia Glee Club.
  - William Wood Glass Jr. to Ada Bantz, 1895 (Box-folder 23:3)
    In a letter dated October 30, 1895 William Glass wrote to Ada about the fire at the University of Virginia, how great the faculty was, and how they were able to keep classes going.
  - William Wood Glass Jr. to Ada Bantz, 1896-1905; n. d. (Box-folder 23:4)
  - C. H. E. Dunn and Dudley W. Gregory to Ada, 1891-1896, 10 items. (Box-folder 23:5)
    There is correspondence about stamping from engravers who were also friends of Ada and her mother.
  - D. B. Greigg, 1895, There is correspondence with pastor D. B. Greigg from Baltimore, Maryland about visiting. (Box-folder 23:6)
  - Bertha (Bert) Hall, 1900-1901; 1914, 20 items. (Box-folder 23:7)
  - Dora Hall, 1897-1901, 13 items. (Box-folder 23:8)
    An 1898 letter refers to "Hurrah for Dewey" and says New Yorkers are supportive but not showing excitement. She imagined there would be more excitement in Washington, D. C.
  - Paul Allan Hall to Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1896-1900 April, 18 items. (Box-folder 23:9)
  - Paul Allan Hall to Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1900 May-December, 8 items. (Box-folder 23:10)
  - Hall Family (Paul, Ada, and Tom), 1897; 1901; n.d., 12 items. (Box-folder 24:1)
  - Paul Allan Hall letters from William Powell, 1901, 2 items (which appear to be love letters from Billy to Paul). (Box-folder 24:2)
  - Hall Census Record, 1900, 2 items. (Box-folder 24:3)
  - Hartman Correspondence, 1900-1950; n.d., 11 items. (Box-folder 24:4)
  - Hartmans, Harmans genealogical information and the University of Virginia, n.d., 27 items. (Box-folder 24:5)
  - Frank Joliffe and Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1899; 1901, 10 items. (Box-folder 24:6)
    Frank Joliffe, a friend of Ada's family, who answered her advertisement for a pen pal. He was divorced and was in love with Ada.
  - Nan and Harry Bantz Krebs to Ada, 1888-1900, 32 items. (Box-folder 24:7)
  - Nan and Harry Krebs, 1901-1910, 37 items. (Box-folder 24:8)
  - Nan and Harry Krebs, 1911-1937; n.d, 25 items. (Box-folder 24:9)
  - Mac to Ada (friend of her father and traveling shoe salesman who was enamored with Ada), 1881-1893 June, 18 items. (Box-folder 24:10)
  - Mac to Ada (friend of her father and traveling shoe salesman who was enamored with Ada), 1893 July-1895 April, 21 items. (Box-folder 24:11)
  - Mac to Ada (friend of her father and traveling shoe salesman who was enamored with Ada), 1895 May-1896; n.d., 18 items. (Box-folder 25:1)
  - Dr. Hunter Holmes McGuire, 1901, 4 items. (Box-folder 25:2)
  - Thomas Jefferson Manning, 1896-1897, 10 items. (Box-folder 25:3)
    Ada's pen pal from Wooster, Massachussetts, Thomas Jefferson Manning wrote about the inauguration of President William McKinley.
  - General and Mrs. Perry L. Miles to Ada, 1946-1950, 9 items. (Box-folder 25:4)
    General and Mrs. Miles were friends of Mr. and Mrs. Beardsworth and wrote correspondence about their health and their travels.
  - Correspondence miscellaneous, 1901; 1903, 2 items. (Box-folder 25:5)
    Includes a letter from John F. Cornish to Miss Alice Young about helping the Suel family; and a letter from attorney John S. Wise to Mrs. John M. Kinney about finding her a position and another letter about her husband's death.
  - Sidney Moss, 1912-1913, 2 items. (Box-folder 25:6)
    His letters thank Mr. and Mrs. Beardsworth for their kindness and he wrote about being a student at the University of Virginia.
  - Newspaper Clippings, n. d., 36 items. (Box-folder 25:7)
  - Thomas Nolan to Ada, 1895, 13 items. (Box-folder 25:8)
    Pen Pal, Thomas Nolan (Editor of the Weekly Sentinel, Racine & Milwaukee, Ws.) wrote to Ada "Every woman here is half a man, and would like to be the other half."
  - Thomas Nolan to Ada, 1896-1897; n.d., 27 items. (Box-folder 25:9)
    Thomas Nolan wrote to Ada about the differences in social life between the people of the North and the South. The people of the South make "more display in wedding than we do in the North." He also wrote that bicycling for women was "unbecoming" and "immodest."
  - General and Mrs. Alexander McCanell Patch (1889-1945) (WWII commander, 4-Star General) to Ada, 1920-1945; n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 25:10)
    General Patch was an Assistant Professor of Military Science at the Staunton Military Academy and was a friend of Mr. and Mrs. Beardsworth. He was promoted to a four star general after his death in 1945.
  - Pen Pal, n. d., 1 item. (Box-folder 25:11)
    Miss Laura Ranson responds to an advertisement in the newspaper for a pen pal and promised to divulge her real name if the correspondence went well.
  - Ada- Postal Position, 1898-1901 April, 22 items. (Box-folder 25:12)
    Ada wrote to political allies and influential friends asking them to help her obtain a postal position. Correspondents include State Senator John Scott, Senator John W. Daniel, Richard Evelyn Byrd, H. L. Barbour, Charles H. Bellows, General Thomas L. Rosser, S. M. Chiles, George B. Thornfelt, and James Hay. Her friends wrote letters on her behalf but she did not score well on her postal examination.
  - Ada for Postal Position, 1901 May - 1903; n. d., 30 items. (Box-folder 25:13)
    Correspondents include General Curtis Guild, A. R. Pendleton, Louis E. McComas and George B. Shoenfelt.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1901, 16 items. (Box-folder 26:1)
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz Beardsworth and her family, 1892-1898, 20 items. (Box-folder 26:2)
    Powell wrote to Ada and her mother and thanked them for presents and told them about his toys, dolls, and playing golf. There are also letters from Billy's father about his son's schedule and mentions that he hopes they are not spoiling him.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz Beardsworth and her family, 1899-1900, 17 items. (Box-folder 26:3)
    Powell wrote about dancing the "Boston dip," riding his bicycle, calling himself Ada's partner in wheeling.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz Beardsworth and her family, 1902, 31 items. (Box-folder 26:4)
    Powell mentioned the death of Charles Broadway Rouss (letter dated March 9, 1902) death of Ada's Aunt Helen (March 23, 1902). He also wrote about a new game called ping pong (April 19, 1902) and the Wizard of Oz as an opera (December 29, 1902).
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz Beardsworth and her family, 1904-1905 (Box-folder 26:5)
    Powell wrote of his concern for Ada's mother, Annie Bantz, "Toodle-Doo" who died in May 1905.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz Beardsworth and her family, 1906-1907, 28 items. (Box-folder 26:6)
    Powell wrote about going to a masquerade party as a French maid, and about his interests in books, movies, tennis, golf, horseback riding, rollerskating, banjo, dances, and plays. He also mentioned going to Amherst College in Massachusetts and a trip to the Jamestown Exposition, his initiation to Psi Upsilon House, and attractive girls at Smith College.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz Beardsworth and her family, 1908-1910, 33 items. (Box-folder 26:7)
    Powell wrote about college life, visits home to Cleveland, trips to Wheeling, West Virginia, and Pittsburg, Pennsylvania. He also wrote about his best friend from childhood, Leonard Hanna.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz, 1911-1913, 18 items. (Box-folder 26:8)
    Powell wrote about his commencement exercises at Amherst and his advertising job with Sherwin-Williams Paint Company. He mentioned that Ada opened an art shop and the passing of Ada's father, T. Marion Bantz. He published articles for The Spectrum. He also mentioned that the articles in the newspapers were all about World War I. He told Ada that he was thinking of going on the road for the Detroit White Lead Works, a minor company owned by Sherwin-Williams, but he was concerned about the amount of travel and leaving his father alone.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz, 1914, 15 items. (Box-folder 27:1)
    Powell wrote in admiration of Ada's art work and inquired about her sales. He told her that he was writing for home decorating magazines. He had an article accepted by "Surburban Life" for twenty five dollars. He had a pen name or nome de plume called "Jeannette Cort." He tried to visit Ada but was sick in Winchester. He wrote, "Your letter has just come and finds me a sick woman" and wanted Ada to come see him. There is also information about plays that Billy wrote for a sales campaign waged by Sherwin-Williams. It was called "Those Happy Campaign Days" and was performed by the Sherwin-Williams staff.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz, 1915, 35 items. (Box-folder 27:2)
    Billy's father, Dr. Hunter Powell died of heart failure. Billy was promoted to Assistant Advertising Manager and gave motivation talks to the sales staff of Sherwin-Williams. There is a news clipping of Powell speaking at the Dayton Advertising Club. He also wrote articles on home decorating. He mentioned his invention of a new game called, Going To Market, similar to Authors. [Going To Market exists today but is rare and the invention is loosely and inaccurately attributed to the CEO of Knox Gelatin.] Billy met with Knox Gelatin, Beech-Nut, Eastman's Kodak, Walk-Over Shoe, Libbie Food Company, Proctor and Gamble, and Welch Grape Juice to obtain their cooperation with the game. He wrote many letters describing the progress of his game and offering to sell it to her. Also in one of his letters he wrote about spending the summer with President Garfield's grandson. He wrote more articles for House and Garden and Countryside. There are also unidentified photographs of cartoon figures of himself and his friends on postcards.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz, 1916-1917, 33 items. (Box-folder 27:3)
    Billy wrote to Ada about his friend, Leonard Hanna, Jr., his trip to Niagara Falls, Ada's trip to Brazil, and attendance at the Yale-Harvard game. He wrote about his work for the Y.M.C.A organizing entertainment committees in various towns while he waited to hear from the Red Cross. He wrote to Ada about war, Camp Lee, red tape with the Draft Board and his eventual sailing to France for his work with the Y.M.C.A. in Paris. Mentions that Ada had taken in boarders.
  - May William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz, 1918-1920, 15 items. (Box-folder 27:4)
    There is a letter from Billy's Aunt Sophye Baker to Ada telling her that he was in Glasgow and a letter from Elizabeth about him being in London. In 1919 he obtained a position with Sherwin-Williams in their London office, Fuller and Smith. There is a letter from Ada to Billy about how she wished she could obtain a secretary position there. Powell wrote about sailing on board "The Adriatic." He wrote about becoming friends with Lady Duff Gordon who had a cabin next door. He also mentioned Lord and Lady Londonderry, Nora Phipps and Pauline Astor. Also in 1919 he returned to the United States and worked for Vanity Fair Silk Mills in Reading, Pennsylvania where he wrote advertising for them. He said, "love the work and think it is going to grow into a big business someday."
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz, 1920 June-December, 15 items. (Box-folder 27:5)
    Powell mentioned his friend Sherwin Cottingham who was the son of the owner of Sherwin-Williams. Powell talked about Cottingham's engagement and marriage to English prima donna Maggie Teyte, an English soprano, and a well known opera singer. Billy also told Ada he was sorry to hear about Uncle Julius's death and asked if he left a will. Ada was trying to obtain a secretarial job.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz, 1921, 28 items. (Box-folder 27:6)
    Powell was admitted into St. Luke's hospital in New York for pleurisy and went to Lake Placid to recover. Later he went on a trip to Cairo, Egypt and saw the crowning of King Faroud. His sentiments toward British rule were very positive as he wrote, "I hate to think what would happen here without English guidance."
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz, 1922-1924, 23 items. (Box-folder 27:7)
    Ada accompanied her husband to Camp Terra Alta in the summers where he taught music. Powell left Sherwin-Williams for the Tracy-Parry Advertising Company.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz, 1925-1926, 31 items. (Box-folder 27:8)
    Powell gave Ada advice on taking a cruise to Europe. He also recommended that she should experience air travel at least once. Powell began a close friendship with prize fighter, Gene Tunney. He also mentioned his cousin from Virginia, John Powell, the famous pianist, composer, and staunch supporter of eugenics.
  - William Baker Powell to Ada Bantz, 1927-1931; n.d., 27 items. (Box-folder 27:9)
    There is a news clipping from The New Yorker about how it was first erroneously reported that a boy scout had saved Gene Tunney when he fell on the ice but actually it was 5' 4" Powell who was wearing his camping clothes. Powell mentioned that he was writing for The New Yorker. He also took a cruise with Leonard Hanna, Jr., Gene Tunney, and Sherwin Coltingham to Europe on the "R M S Mauretania." Powell also mentioned the Barcelona Exposition and wanting to accompany Leonard to work in Hollywood. He attended dinners with Claudette Colbert and Ira Claire. He also got commissions for ads or articles for The Graphic and The Bystander. Often Powell would rely on Ada to gather research for him for his articles. Powell also mentioned that families were being hurt and losing so much from the unemployment and depression. He made a reference to prohibition as well.
  - William Baker Powell "Billy" to Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1932-1938 (Box-folder 28:1)
    Powell obtained a job rewriting the radio news each day and reporting it to the passengers on board the "S. S. Rex" of the Italian line. He also had an advertising account with the Grace Line. Powell wrote to Ada about the death of Cornelia Shriner. In 1937 Billy wrote that, "he has never been poorer and needs jobs in the worst way." Powell mentioned the war in his letter dated Sept 28, 1938. He was also writing a couple of articles for the Polish Embassy in connection with the World's Fair in New York. He also mentioned Cole's musical (Cole Porter's Leave It To Me).
  - William Baker Powell "Billy" to Ada Bantz Beardsworth, 1939-1947 (Box-folder 28:2)